In the previous video, we talked
在上一段视频中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
about how to use back propagation
我们谈到了怎样使用反向传播算法
to compute the derivatives of your cost function.
计算代价函数的导数
In this video, I want
在这段视频中
to quickly tell you about one implementational detail of
我想快速地向你介绍一个细节的实现过程
unrolling your parameters from
怎样把你的参数
matrices into vectors, which we
从矩阵展开成向量
need in order to use the advanced optimization routines.
以便我们在高级最优化步骤中的使用需要
Concretely, let's say
具体来讲
you've implemented a cost function
你执行了代价函数costFunction
that takes this input, you know, parameters
输入参数是theta
theta and returns the cost function and returns derivatives.
函数返回值是代价函数以及导数值
Then you can pass this to
然后你可以将返回值
an advanced authorization algorithm by fminunc
传递给高级最优化算法fminunc
and fminunc
顺便提醒
isn't the only one by the way.
fminunc并不是唯一的算法
There are also other advanced authorization algorithms.
你也可以使用别的优化算法
But what all of them
但它们的功能
do is take those input
都是取出这些输入值
pointedly the cost function,
@costFunction
and some initial value of theta.
以及theta值的一些初始值
And both, and these
并且这些程序
routines assume that theta and
都假设theta
the initial value of theta, that
和这些theta初始值
these are parameter vectors, maybe
都是参数向量
Rn or Rn plus 1.
也许是n或者n+1阶
But these are vectors and it
但它们都是向量
also assumes that, you know, your cost
同时假设这个代价函数
function will return as
第二个返回值
a second return value this
也就是gradient值
gradient which is also Rn
也是n阶或者n+1阶
and Rn plus 1. So also a vector.
所以它也是一个向量
This worked fine when we
这部分在我们使用逻辑回归的时候
were using logistic progression but
运行顺利
now that we're using a neural
但现在 对于神经网络
network our parameters are
我们的参数将不再是
no longer vectors, but instead
向量
they are these matrices where for
而是矩阵了
a full neural network we would
因此对于一个完整的神经网络
have parameter matrices theta 1, theta 2, theta 3
我们的参数矩阵为θ(1) θ(2) θ(3)
that we might represent in Octave
在Octave中我们可以设为
as these matrices theta 1, theta 2, theta 3.
Theta1 Theta2 Theta3
And similarly these gradient
类似的 这些梯度项gradient
terms that were expected to return.
也是需要得到的返回值
Well, in the previous video we
那么在之前的视频中
showed how to compute these
我们演示了如何计算
gradient matrices, which was
这些梯度矩阵
capital D1, capital D2,
它们是D(1) D(2) D(3)
capital D3, which we
在Octave中
might represent an octave as matrices D1, D2, D3.
我们用矩阵D1 D2 D3来表示
In this video I want
在这节视频中
to quickly tell you about the
我想很快地向你介绍
idea of how to take
怎样取出这些矩阵
these matrices and unroll them into vectors.
并且将它们展开成向量
So that they end up
以便它们最终
being in a format suitable for
成为恰当的格式
passing into as theta here off for getting
能够传入这里的Theta
out for a gradient there.
并且得到正确的梯度返回值gradient
Concretely, let's say we
具体来说
have a neural network with one
假设我们有这样一个神经网络
input layer with ten units,
其输入层有10个输入单元
hidden layer with ten units
隐藏层有10个单元
and one output layer with
最后的输出层
just one unit, so s1
只有一个输出单元
is the number of units in layer one
因此s1等于第一层的单元数
and s2 is the
s2等于第二层的单元数
number of units in layer two, and s3 is a number
s3等于第三层的
of units in layer three.
单元个数
In this case, the dimension of
在这种情况下
your matrices theta and
矩阵θ的维度
D are going to be
和矩阵D的维度
given by these expressions.
将由这些表达式确定
For example, theta one
比如说
is going to a 10 by 11 matrix and so on.
θ(1)是一个10x11的矩阵 以此类推
So in if you want
因此 在Octave中
to convert between these matrices.
如果你想将这些矩阵
vectors.
转化为向量
What you can do is take
那么你要做的
your theta 1, theta
是取出你的Theta1 Theta2
2, theta 3, and write this
Theta3
piece of code and this will
然后使用这段代码
take all the elements of
这段代码将取出
your three theta matrices and
三个θ矩阵中的所有元素
take all the elements
也就是说取出Theta1
of theta one, all the
的所有元素
elements of theta 2, all the
Theta2的所有元素
elements of theta 3,
Theta3的所有元素
and unroll them and put
然后把它们全部展开
all the elements into a big long vector.
成为一个很长的向量
Which is thetaVec and similarly
也就是thetaVec
the second command would take
同样的 第二段代码
all of your D matrices and
将取出D矩阵的所有元素
unroll them into a big
然后展开
long vector and call them
成为一个长向量
DVec. And finally
被叫做DVec
if you want to go back from
最后 如果你想从向量表达
the vector representations to the matrix representations.
返回到矩阵表达式的话
What you do to get back
你要做的是
to theta one say is take
比如想再得到Theta1
thetaVec and pull
那么取thetaVec
out the first 110 elements.
抽出前110个元素
So theta 1 has 110
因此
elements because it's a
Theta1就有110个元素
10 by 11 matrix so that
因为它应该是一个10x11的矩阵
pulls out the first 110 elements
所以 抽出前110个元素
and then you can
然后你就能使用
use the reshape command to reshape those back into theta 1.
reshape矩阵变维命令来重新得到Theta1
And similarly, to get
同样类似的
back theta 2 you pull
要重新得到Theta2矩阵
out the next 110 elements and reshape it.
你需要抽出下一组110个元素并且重新组合
And for theta 3, you pull out
然后对于Theta3
the final eleven elements and run
你需要抽出最后11个元素
reshape to get back the theta 3.
然后执行reshape命令 重新得到Theta3
Here's a quick Octave demo of that process.
以下是这一过程的Octave演示
So for this example
对于这一个例子
let's set theta 1 equal
让我们假设Theta1
to be ones of 10 by
为一个10x11的单位矩阵
11, so it's a matrix of all ones. And
因此它每一项都为1
just to make this easier seen,
为了更易看清
let's set that to be 2
让我们把Theta2设为
times ones, 10 by
一个10行11列矩阵
11 and let's
每个元素都为2
set theta 3 equals 3
然后设Theta3 是一个1x11的矩阵
times 1's of 1 by 11.
每个元素都为3
So this is 3
因此 这样我们得到三个独立的矩阵
separate matrices: theta 1, theta 2, theta 3.
Theta1 Theta2 Theta3
We want to put all of these as a vector.
现在我们想把所有这些矩阵变成一个向量
ThetaVec equals theta
thetaVec =
1; theta 2
[Theta1(:); Theta2(:); Theta3(:)];
theta 3.
好的
Right, that's a colon
注意中间有冒号
in the middle and like so
像这样
and now thetavec is
现在thetaVec矩阵
going to be a very long vector.
就变成了一个很长的向量
That's 231 elements.
含有231个元素
If I display it, I find
如果把它打出来
that this very long vector with
我们就能看出它是一个很长的向量
all the elements of the first
包括第一个矩阵的所有元素
matrix, all the elements of
第二个矩阵的所有元素
the second matrix, then all the elements of the third matrix.
以及第三个矩阵的所有元素
And if I want to get back
如果我想重新得到
my original matrices, I can
我最初的三个矩阵
do reshape thetaVec.
我可以对thetaVec使用reshape命令
Let's pull out the first 110
抽出前110个元素
elements and reshape them to a 10 by 11 matrix.
将它们重组为一个10x11的矩阵
This gives me back theta 1.
这样我又再次得到了Theta1矩阵
And if I then pull
然后我再取出
out the next 110 elements.
接下来的110个元素
So that's indices 111 to 220.
也就是111到220号元素
I get back all of my 2's.
我就又重组还原了第二个矩阵
And if I go
最后
from 221 up to
再抽出221到最后一个元素
the last element, which is
也就是第231个元素
element 231, and reshape to
然后重组为1x11的矩阵
1 by 11, I get back theta 3.
我就又得到了Theta3矩阵
To make this process really concrete,
为了使这个过程更形象
here's how we use the unrolling
下面我们来看怎样将这一方法
idea to implement our learning algorithm.
应用于我们的学习算法
Let's say that you have some
假设说你有一些
initial value of the parameters
初始参数值
theta 1, theta 2, theta 3.
θ(1) θ(2) θ(3)
What we're going to do
我们要做的是
is take these and unroll
取出这些参数并且将它们
them into a long vector
展开为一个长向量
we're gonna call initial theta to
我们称之为initialTheta
pass in to fminunc
然后作为theta参数的初始设置
as this initial setting of the parameters theta.
传入函数fminunc
The other thing we need to do is implement the cost function.
我们要做的另一件事是执行代价函数costFunction
Here's my implementation of the cost function.
实现算法如下
The cost function is going to
代价函数costFunction
give us input, thetaVec,
将传入参数thetaVec
which is going to be all
这也是包含
of my parameters vectors that in
我所有参数的向量
the form that's been unrolled into a vector.
是将所有的参数展开成一个向量的形式
So the first thing I'm going to
因此我要做的第一件事是
do is I'm going to use
我要使用
thetaVec and I'm going to use the reshape functions.
thetaVec和重组函数reshape
So I'll pull out elements from
因此我要抽出thetaVec中的元素
thetaVec and use reshape
然后重组
to get back my
以得到我的初始参数矩阵
original parameter matrices, theta 1, theta 2, theta 3.
θ(1) θ(2) θ(3)
So these are going to be matrices that I'm going to get.
所以这些是我需要得到的矩阵
So that gives me a
因此 这样我就有了
more convenient form in which
一个使用这些矩阵的
to use these matrices so that I
更方便的形式
can run forward propagation and
这样我就能执行前向传播
back propagation to compute my
和反向传播
derivatives, and to compute my cost function j of theta.
来计算出导数 以求得代价函数的J(θ)
And finally, I can then
最后
take my derivatives and unroll
我可以取出这些导数值 然后展开它们
them, to keeping the elements
让它们保持和我展开的θ值
in the same ordering as I did when I unroll my thetas.
同样的顺序
But I'm gonna unroll D1, D2,
我要展开D1 D2 D3
D3, to get gradientVec
来得到gradientVec
which is now what my cost function can return.
这个值可由我的代价函数返回
It can return a vector of these derivatives.
它可以以一个向量的形式返回这些导数值
So, hopefully, you now have
好了 希望你现在
a good sense of how to
对怎样进行参数的矩阵表达式
convert back and forth between
和向量表达式
the matrix representation of the
之间的转换
parameters versus the vector representation of the parameters.
有了一个更清晰的认识
The advantage of the matrix
使用矩阵表达式
representation is that when
的好处是
your parameters are stored as
当你的参数以矩阵的形式储存时
matrices it's more convenient when
你在进行正向传播
you're doing forward propagation and
和反向传播时
back propagation and it's easier
你会觉得更加方便
when your parameters are stored as
当你将参数储存为矩阵时
matrices to take advantage
一大好处是
of the, sort of, vectorized implementations.
充分利用了向量化的实现过程
Whereas in contrast the advantage of
相反地
the vector representation, when you
向量表达式的优点是
have like thetaVec or DVec is that
如果你有像thetaVec或者DVec这样的矩阵
when you are using the advanced optimization algorithms.
当你使用一些高级的优化算法时
Those algorithms tend to
这些算法通常要求
assume that you have
你所有的参数
all of your parameters unrolled into a big long vector.
都要展开成一个长向量的形式
And so with what we just
希望通过我们刚才介绍的内容
went through, hopefully you can now quickly
你能够根据需要 更加轻松地
convert between the two as needed.
在两种形式之间转换